<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="inst-quickinstall">
	<title>Quick installation</title>
	<section>
		<title>Prerequisites</title>
		<para>
			DNet eBusiness Suite requires Java 6 or later to be installed. It is
			available from
			<link linkend="http://www.java.com">http://www.java.com</link>
		</para>
		<para>
			Depending on your environment setup, you may need to configure the
			amount of memory allocated by the operating system to the JVM (Java
			Virtual Machine). Please see
			<link linkend="out-of-memory">Prevent or fix Out of Memory Errors</link>
			section below.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Installing from the zip download</title>
		<para>
			Extract the contents of the archive somewhere on your computer, lets
			say
			<literal>C:/dnet</literal>
			Inside you should find a
			<literal>virgo-tomcat-server-xxx</literal>
			folder which contains a Virgo web-server already configured to run
			DNet; xxx stands for the server version, at the time of writing this
			document is 3.0.1-RELEASE. So go to
			<literal>virgo-tomcat-server-xxx/bin</literal>
			folder and double-click the
			<literal>startup.bat</literal>
			.
		</para>
		<para>It opens a console window showing the steps performed during
			startup. Wait to finish then go to your browser and type in the
			adress bar:</para>
		<para>
			<link linkend="http://localhost:8081/nan21.dnet.core.welcome">http://localhost:8081/nan21.dnet.core.welcome
			</link>
		</para>
		<para>Click the logo which redirects you to the application setup
			section. Sign-in with user 'admin' and password 'admin'.</para>
		<para>Follow on-screen instructions.</para>
		<note>
			The default configuration uses H2 database and creates its files in
			$USER_HOME/dnet_ebs/dnet_db_h2 directory, where $USER_HOME is your
			user home on you computer.
		</note>
	</section>
	<section id="out-of-memory">
		<title>Prevent or fix Out of Memory Errors</title>
		<para>Java applications run in a "container" called "Java virtual
			machine" (JVM) not directly within an operating system. Whenever such
			a JVM process is started by the operating system, it is allocated a
			certain amount of memory so that the JVM can use it to run its
			applications. By default, this amount is rather small, usually 64Mb
			regardless of how much memory is available on your machine. Larger
			Java applications need more memory to run properly and when the JVM
			cannot allocate more it crashes with "Out of Memory Error". To
			prevent or fix such problems, the amount of memory allocated to JVM
			needs to be increased.</para>
		<para> By default the demo application in the distribution package
			starts Virgo web-server with the proper values to run DNet, however you may
			change these in case you need.</para>
		<para>
			On Windows open
			<literal>virgo-tomcat-server-xxx/bin/setenv.bat</literal>
			, on Linux open
			<literal>virgo-tomcat-server-xxx/bin/setenv.sh</literal>
			and change the
			<literal>JAVA_OPTS</literal>
			values provided according to your needs.
		</para>
		<para>Please check the Java documentation for more details on JVM
			startup configuration options.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>